So here's a question which frequently
comes up.
There's this idea in your teachings that
patiently enduring mental pressures is
what purifies the mind from defilements.
But it's hard to square this with how
the Buddha often encouraged disciples to
be diligent and strive to abandon unh
wholesome states. You know that's a
simile about your hair being on fire and
so on.
So, one cannot deny that enduring
certain things is an important part of
the training. But if that's all you do
and you never make an active effort to
remove what is unh wholesome from your
mind, then how can it ever truly become
pure? >> What would you say? That's a that's a
>> What would you say? That's a that's a
frequent question which we hear.
>> Yeah. Well, the confusion comes from
the person's understanding of what an
unh wholesome state is. So the natural
tendency is like you know you you come
from the starting point.
What you have is basically your your
mind revolving around certain thoughts
like you know memories of sensual things
that you experienced in the past or
things you want in the future or
somebody upset you or something. And
then the easy assumption to make is that
oh well if I just stop these thoughts
themselves from coming up. Well first of
all you could you you associate that
with the unh wholesome state. It's these
thoughts that if I can just somehow deal
with them suppress them my mind will be
pure. But what you fail to realize is
what somebody who has that view is that
the actual defilement like the greed,
aversion, delusion like what is greed?
Greed is leaning towards pleasure.
Aversion is leaning away from
displeasure. Um delusion or distraction
is kind of yeah leaning away from the
neutrality of the neutral of the neutral
feeling. uh because you know it's it's
somehow not enough in and of itself. So
then you realize well the defilement is
not the presence of pleasure, the
presence of pain,
it's your inability to well your
tendency to want to act out of it let's
say. So then when you have these um you
know kind of persistent pressures in
your mind instead of blaming those
things which is kind of what the that
type of view comes from. It's like even
if you don't think of it that way you
imply that through getting rid of the
objects by focusing on your breath or
whatever you're fixing the problem. But
no, it's like the problem will be fixed
actually when in regard to those same
objects and those same thoughts, there
is no movement, no internal kind of um
need to to get them if they're pleasant,
to run away from them if they're
unpleasant. Uh so that that should be
your aim as as that should be your
measure for what development is because
otherwise it's like um you know you you
can you can say whatever you want that
that you can um jump super high when
there's no gravity anymore.
But what's the point of that? Like
what's the point of that your mind can
be peaceful when these things are not
there? when you have suppressed those
pressures. >> Yeah. That's a very circumstantial piece
>> Yeah. That's a very circumstantial piece
now.
>> Exactly. So then you want to recognize
like if you I mean even if you think
about it just just um on the level of
how the world works,
there is no way that you will
permanently be able to shelter yourself
from these things. like things happen.
Um unexpected situations come up. As as
much uh sense restraint as you might
have been practicing, things will come
through sometimes that will
bring up those those um kind of minds
spinning around this or that. And then
you have to recognize, wait, no, the
problem is not the object. As a Buddhist
said, the the
beautiful things in the world are not
what sensuality is. It's your lustful
intention in regard to those things
>> that constitute sensuality. So then
that's the whole uh
this whole need to discern the sign of
your mind because then you start to
recognize well it has nothing to do with
these objects like these objects can
remain there forever if they want
because if if like if you interpret that
that statement to mean oh well the
beautiful things remain there in the
world meaning out there in like the
external in the city or something but no
it's the internal
the world of your own senses and sense
objects like these things as would say
they belong to mara and mara is in
control of them.
>> So in that sense on that internal level
that's what the world is and these
things will remain there. You cannot to
some extent they will remain there. You
can be sensor strained and you should be
but sensor restraint is not about like
unfortunately that's how is interpreted
often but it's not about preventing
uh these things as much as you can as a
blanket effort. It's about well when
when the seeking of these things would
be for me rooted in sensuality I don't
do so
>> when the kind of um focusing on the
dissatis unsatisfying aspect of these
things when that would be rooted in
aversion I don't attend in that
direction so that is literally how the
sutas describe sense restraint cuz it's
it it already comes from that
understanding where you don't blame the
objects themselves and even the the
feelings that they may arouse in you.
You don't blame that for the problem.
You actually see your mind and you see
this yeah need to act out as the actual
problem. So by enduring the pressure,
you're actually
enduring the pressure which requires you
to be, you know, keeping the precepts
and and practicing sensory strength. So
it doesn't mean that when you endure the
pressure, you're kind of letting your
mind indulge in these thoughts. It's
quite the opposite. It's like you you
will have to learn to rein the mind back
in in order to start enduring these
things properly
>> for because if you are welcoming the
sensual thoughts, welcoming the thoughts
of ill will, picking them up, revolving
around them, um you know, proliferating
these narratives and and things that
your mind will be trying to push on you,
you're not enduring it for that very
reason. Like you're going the path of
least resistance.
>> Yeah. So there is such a thing as mental
restraint as well. So earlier you were
referring about Mara like doesn't really
matter where you go because
>> you're enclosed within the within his
range. Yeah.
>> Within his range which includes also
thoughts as the as the objects of of the
sixth sense.
>> And it doesn't even matter which thought
you choose because the craving as to say
it will land anywhere. So if you just
pick an object that your kind of
>> intellectual reasoning
>> tells you is less bad than the others
well you will be as as people would
often do like oh the breath is a neutral
object therefore if I just focus on this
I will be taking my mind away from the
bad stuff but that's again completely
missing the point that it's not the
stuff that is the reason for your
craving it's that internal attitude of
your mind that will shift towards
anything in the entire universe
regardless of its of its content. So if
you see that that is the the source of
the whole thing then you realize well
replacing the object makes absolutely no
no difference
>> because you could have a sensual mind
even in relation to just breathing in
and breathing out. sensual or you could
say passionate mind like a mind that
that uh is dependent on something
>> and that is the problem. That is the
thing that
>> causes you to be subjected to suffering
that dependence.
>> So then you realize that actually if you
were to
let's say
that's why it's the middle way. So you
don't allow yourself to give in to the
obvious path of indulgence,
but you also don't go in the opposite
direction of trying to remove the things
that are trying to bait you. And that's
where you find that middle way, which is
where you neither push forward nor stand
still, as the sutas would say. Um, and
then you have the the the pressuring
thing there, but you are rightly
recognizing where the line is and where
your engagement and picking up of those baits
engagement and picking up of those baits
actually begins.
>> Yeah. And then by by turning yourself to
stay on that level, you're actually
taming permanently forever what the lust
actually is. Because you will not be
able to prevent these things from
baiting you. Even the Buddha as as after
his awakening would say for the
seven years following his awakening,
Mara was still trying to gain access to
him. So you could see even after
becoming an araj you wouldn't be able to
stop this these invitations of mara from
coming but if you fully discern that
kind of being an island unto yourself as
the sutas would say that's how you
develop it by understanding well it
doesn't matter how much this stuff comes
up but through uh I ear nose tongue body
mind it doesn't matter what things are
being presented through those six
gateways. It's my choice to cultivate certain
It's my choice to cultivate certain
attitudes in regard to those things.
>> It's my it's my choice not to want to
endure them. And and in fact, there's
one sutra where it explicitly says, "Who
is the one who has gone beyond who has
crossed over to the farther shore?" And
it says it's the one who can endure the
pressure of the eye, of the ear, of the
nose, of the tongue, of the body, of the
mind, of mono.
>> Yeah, I think it also says that that's
necessary to gain Janna.
>> Yeah, exactly. So, because well, that's
an a whole other rabbit hole. But the
the view of what Janna is nowadays
precisely reflects that wrong view of
people thinking that is the object of of
the the object that the mind happens to
associate the pressure with. By removing
the object,
>> yeah,
>> I supposedly fix the problem and I enter
this transient transient state of almost
being on vacation. But the actual Janna
would be when in fact the sutas describe
it that way as well in regard to
pleasant sights, pleasant sounds,
pleasant um smells, tastes and touches.
Those remain there the same place where
there always been. But internally there
is no more passion towards those things.
And for that you need to allow those
things to arise. How will you develop
dispassion towards this
>> if this is not present?
>> Yeah. But this now doesn't mean that
somebody needs to deliberately seek out
provocative sites in order to tame their
lust or their aversion
>> because this is on a much more general
level. You already have those sense
bases. There is already experience going
on. It cannot be like that.
>> Yeah.
>> So if somebody thinks, "Oh, I want to
test myself. let's go back to a more
let's say urban environment and see how
my mind reacts. That's a that's already
entirely missing the point now.
>> No. And that's why the whole uh training
of the middle way that we described the
the foremost way to do that is the monk
life. So it's like living away from
these things. Ironically that's how you
would be able to properly face them.
>> Yeah. Because if you are exposing
yourself to them, that view already
again you're putting the emphasis on the
objects and you're overlooking the fact
that more often than not
you're very the very attitude of your
mind towards the objects that's getting
you to go there in the first place.
Basically the the passion is already
there. >> Yeah. It's not seen
>> Yeah. It's not seen
>> the perception of these things as
gratifying is already there. And so you
might be kind of training some kind of
willpower to say no to the wild animal
that you've made wilder by going there,
but you're certainly not decreasing the
wildness of the animal.
>> Yeah. So
you actually have to go the opposite way
of keeping the precepts practicing
sensor strain as we said before. But
then you know
you don't keep kind of running as far as
you can in that direction because that's
another trap. It's like thinking the
more I restrain the the less kind of
contact I have with these things the
more secluded from passion I will be.
And that would be another mistake like
now you're going too far in the opposite
direction. So you you keep the precepts
and you establish yourself in this
container of you know a certain
diminished exposure to these things but
then within that even within that they
will still be coming up
>> and that is where you have to allow
them. >> Exactly. That's where like being fully
>> Exactly. That's where like being fully
established in in in uh the precepts
being fully established in sense
restraint in wakefulness in uh clear
clear comprehension as would describe it
then you're in a position to actually
abandon the five hindrances where you
would be neither pushing like neither
kind of
letting yourself go with the momentum of
these thoughts which is what you would
be doing before. Nor are you doing doing
what most people think practice is,
which is to try to suppress those
objects as as much as you can.
>> And then you start to realize that
middleman there, which is where the
chitta actually is. It's like you
realize yeah there I can have the exact
same object completely unchanged but the
cheetah internally has no interest in it
anymore. So the same significance is
there the same like you would clearly
recognize this is the exact same thing
that was arousing lust in the past. You
haven't like turn your gaze away from
it. It's still there and you see but now
there is no lust. So that's what the
sutas would call the opening amidst
confinement. It's like in regard to the
things that's continue to be pleasant,
continue to be beautiful, you haven't
like uh put a mask on them so that you
know the animal doesn't react. No, the
animal has become dispassionate towards
the same thing. And then that's where
you start to realize why the Buddha used
these simileies of um like the the
clever cook having to pick up the signs
of the king to to describe like this
principle of recognizing your mind i.e
recognizing where those unh wholesome
states actually are. Going back to the
to that original question, it's not
something that you would be able to spot
by just looking. Oh, I have such
thoughts arising in my mind. This thing
clearly is what the problem is and
that's where it ends. If it were that
easy, then you know, as the Buddha said,
the the whole dharma, he didn't want to
teach it
>> because it would be too subtle and it
would go uh go over people's heads
precisely because of this. Because even
when the the untrained mind tries to do
something about the problem, it aims at
the objects, aims at the at the um
>> because that is where it always was due
to not having retained the sensuality
first. >> Yeah. That's always where your emphasis
>> Yeah. That's always where your emphasis
was. Exactly. So that's that's just a
continuation of the same tendency, the
same wrong view that you would have had.
So that's why the selfmodification which
is but you could summarize as the
tendency to to to put the blame on the
objects and try to get rid of them as as
intensely as possible that actually
keeps you within the exact same domain.
It's not that it's taking you far
farther away from sensuality. It kind of
brings you back by trying to go too far.
You actually return to the same uh to
the same domain of mara. And there's
that whole suta where the deer herd. It
says like they by trying to run away
from the
>> hunting ground.
>> Yeah.
>> Eventually they they end up equally
caught as the first deer herd of deer
that were just carelessly eating
everything in that hunting ground. So
the the fourth herd of deer, the smart
ones, what they realize like, wait, we
don't need to run away from this stuff.
We don't need to uh try to hide because
like you know the hunter factually could
be anywhere. What we have to do is
exercise mindfulness but of of the right
kind in regard to the things that are
inside that domain. Which means going
back to what we just said, don't blame
the object.
See what is that internal attitude of
your chitta in regard to it. Is there an
obsessive kind of like impulsive
tendency towards it? And you would see
that kind of thing could come and go
from day to day which already starts to
show you that in regard to the same
thing. >> You mean the impulsivity?
>> You mean the impulsivity?
>> Yeah. Because already starts to show you
well if if if truly the problem was on
this level then this would have to
remain the same always.
>> Yeah.
>> In regard to this object. But no, you
realize that kind of thing that's that's
sometimes like this, sometimes like
that. Well, everything else remains the
same. That already starts to show you
those indirect signs of that chitta. And
that's where you would be able to turn
it away completely to the opposite
direction without actually moving an
inch >> in terms of the place where you were
>> in terms of the place where you were
basically. That's why that's why it's
it's kind of like um well such a subtle
thing because again naturally you think
I just run I just move away from this
stuff that's provoking me and that's how
I will be free from it. But it's
actually right where you are. But in in
the in in that level of like the the
domain of mara right where you are
that's where internally the
transformation happens on the level of
your chitta.